So would you say
that the soda paner
is perfectly self-transparent?
Yeah, that's why it's a soda pan.
The right view is a basically self
transparency to the sufficient extent.
to the sufficient extent.
Mhm.
Yeah. And and that's basically
And and that's basically
the combination of
Yeah. Yeah. Well, the the complete
combination is aranche.
Mhm. Mhm.
But there's absolutely no no
contradiction left within you. Um but
that's what I meant by the um
little dust in their eyes, more dust in
their eyes.
What is basically
transparent means you see through
clearly. There is nothing obscuring.
There is nothing obscuring.
It's not a lot of dust.
If you're not as transparent, you have
some dust in your eyes, so you cannot
quite see clearly.
Mhm. Um,
Um,
but someone with a little bit of dust in
their eyes
means Yeah.
they could still hear him.
Yeah. They could still recognize what he was
They could still recognize what he was
talking about. Well, the ones with a
little dust in their eyes, yeah, they
would they would need just
fewer prompts towards uh that oh
developing that transparency, that
recognition of the certain universal
principles, understanding those,
understanding the nature of things that
the fundamental to their own existence
and that's it.
There's nothing else that's being
obscured. Then you have those with more
dust in their eyes. They need to invest
more effort into developing their
transparency. Um
Um
so the really the question is what
transparency is? Yeah, exactly. How does
somebody What is transparency?
What is transparency?
What is selfrespency
is a thread
of practice of effort
that is in common.
Yeah. To somebody who is puja
To somebody who is puja
and somebody who is even
so ifa starts to develop uh self
transparency he's heading towards the
right view. Mhm.
Even if he doesn't necessarily know it,
it the extent of his transparency is
sort of that's what's in common.
At least the idea of the direction that
that's worth developing.
Yeah. And that's why some people in the sutas
And that's why some people in the sutas
when they met the Buddha literally
just heard one sentence from him and
became fully enlightened cuz they've
actually removed everything else that
was obscuring it. they've developed that
transparency to degree necessary.
So that's like that's the kind of that's
the basis of the Buddha's teaching the
practice. If you want to if you're
interested in practicing according to
what the Buddha was talking about then
it's all within this idea of
becoming transparent.
Yeah. Understanding your motives.
Understanding your motives.
Yeah.
Tolerating I was going to ask you that
now. So what
what is the definition of transparent
and non-transparent? What's the
difference? What would be a different
um characteristic of it that you could
differentiate these two things?
So somebody who's transparent has is
clear about their motives.
Yeah. So transparent in regard to what?
Transparent in regard to motivation.
Motivation for what? Well, motivation
for bodily action, for verbal action,
for mental action.
Yeah. Hence that the entire teaching is is is
Hence that the entire teaching is is is
bound and contained within that nature
of action and freedom from it.
What am I doing?
So it's not like I'm not transparent in
regard to such and such thing that I
don't understand. That's not the
transparency we talk about.
Yeah. It's transparency in regard to your own
It's transparency in regard to your own
present here and now pretty much
whatever you're doing, thinking, saying,
transparency in regard to motivation.
Yeah, that's like the most encompassing
that's like the most encompassing
general way you could describe it.
It's kind of Could you say it's like
Yes. It's not being clear about
everything, but just being
Far from it. Far from it.
But just being because there are things
that are not clear. That's the nature.
Exactly. But but it's being clear about the
But but it's being clear about the
direction you're heading in.
Yeah. It's being it's being cleared.
It's it's about being clear about um
actions you're intending. You're about
to intend. Actions you intended. And
it's just the the kind of vague
direction of those actions like like it
might I said vague it might be it might
you might not be able to
like I say not everything is clear but
you just know at this direction is
yeah the content yeah the like oh like
shall I do this or shall I do that I
have an option A and option B so I can
investigate the option A see the
drawbacks of option B I can look at the
drawback All of that is kind of secondary to what
All of that is kind of secondary to what
I'm talking about.
You want to see why are you considering
doing either option A or option B
regardless of the results of option A
and option B.
So even if you cannot see any drawback
in an option A
but you still recognize that it's purely
rooted in your desire for pleasure.
That's it. You shouldn't do it cuz
that's more important where the action
is rooted. The more you reflect and
contemplate that, the more transparent
in regard to your own motivation that
it's there while you want to commit the
action you will become.
In other words, it will take you less
and less effort to see where the action
is rooted in greed, aversion, delusion
or non-greed, non- aversion, non-
delusion the more you invest uh into
seeing it.
So like for for a lay person for example
who is who is not in the environment of
of the um
sense like sense restraint of a monk or
or somebody who has kind of renounced
the world but who wants to practice the
dharma. So like the absolute beginner so
to speak.
Um even that it's the same principle.
You want to be clear
for the reasons
clear about the reasons that are making
you act in that direction or in this
direction choosing this choosing that.
And that applies to any form of action
not just immediate one I'm about to do
now but even my future plans.
Mhm. So like that's that's another
thing. So
as a lay person, oh I want to practice
da. Why why do I want to practice da?
Because I want to be free from
suffering. Okay, that's a good answer.
So where is that suffering that I want
to be free from? Mhm. Is that suffering
in the future? So I'll practice them in
the future. Or is that liability to
suffering in the present? Well, it's in
the present. So how does that liability
suffering in the present manifest to me
really? Well,
through me experiencing unwanted things
through my own actions.
So you want to practice dharma in the
future when you get your conditions
ready while in reality all you need to
do is start recognizing where your
motivation is rooted and you'll be
practicing dharma for the same purpose
of being free from suffering.
Mhm. So you you recognize that
So you you recognize that
can you suffer in any way if you don't
want anything? If you don't want to have
anything and you don't want to keep
anything, no.
no.
And you don't care about losing anything
or you don't care about gaining
anything, can you experience any
discrepancy that would result in
suffering? So can you then suffer if you
don't have any desire whatsoever,
any emotional investment whatsoever?
So then you realize whenever you do
suffer, it's because you're emotionally
invested. And means whenever you're emotionally
And means whenever you're emotionally
invested means you act out of that as
your reason. Yes.
More pleasure. I don't want pain. I want
a distraction. I don't want I don't want
like a nothingness. Neutral feeling.
And so you're you're acting out of that
desire is just simply keeping the whole thing
is just simply keeping the whole thing
going.
Yeah. Yeah. You're sustaining it, you're
maintaining it, you're feeding it. So
the trans the transparency and again can
you develop transparency in regard to
your motivation
if you don't even restrain your actions?
No, if you're physically sort of already
if you're physically sort of already
fully rooted in desire and acting
towards more desire.
No, because those actions are still, you
know, they're keeping it.
Well, exactly. Exactly. They're fully
rooted in that. So, it doesn't matter
how much you might try to mentally
resist. The fact that you're bodily engaging
The fact that you're bodily engaging
with with things that root in desire
means you you are fully within that
cycle. I guess I guess like that's the
things people the practice isn't some
kind of like something that's separate
from your life like you know oh I just
live my life like this and then all
right now I'll do something exactly
that's completely got nothing to do with
basically if you do practice rightly it
will undermine your life it will start
undoing your life
undoing your very ba your very being
because your life your life is
everything that you're doing which is
determined by your
and when the Buddha speaks about the
truth and seeing the truth and so on.
It's not the truth, you know, a secret
that you haven't known. It's the truth
in regard to your own experience
where my actions are rooted.
So you can actually recognize
u what you said earlier on that there
are certain things that are unknown
cannot be known.
Mhm. Cannot be empirically sort of verified.
Cannot be empirically sort of verified.
Yeah.
In this life and that's a fact that is
or even can be but they're not right
now. Exactly. So right now what is
Exactly. So right now what is
empirically verifiable is that these
things cannot be empirically verifiable.
Exactly. And you recognize that
And you recognize that
and you realize and the way the reason
why you can recognize that is because
you realize it was never the point of
figuring these things out.
The point was simply to not maintain
greed, aversion, delusion, not maintain
desire on the level of body action,
speech action, mental action and that's
it. then you don't have a problem with
not knowing things or haven't figured it
out long enough because you you stop
assuming that the answer is at the end
of those things
and you start to see that actually your
attempts to try to find out about these
things exactly that's already rooted in
exactly that's already rooted in
something and if you don't ignore that
that's the lacking of truth not in like
lacking of um experiencing like certain
content or certain answers of your
experience
so that's what I mean like even when
people do a meditation technique that
obviously will involve this kind of time
and then result of some special
experience. They remain ignorant of their motivation
They remain ignorant of their motivation
throughout.
Yeah. Because if you become aware you don't
Because if you become aware you don't
need a technique.
Yeah. That's the field where any effort
That's the field where any effort
applies.
The field of motivation behind me
wanting to go to retreat to do this
technique or do that technique. Why? Oh,
cuz I want to be free from suffering.
What is free from suffering for me? Is
it a special do I assume it's some sort
of experience whereby everything else
will be canceled by it?
or is it something else perhaps? Have I
investigated long enough to see? So
that's the the clearer you are for about
your motives, the clearer you will
become about what your goal is as well.
Mhm. And that's why the Buddha talked about
And that's why the Buddha talked about
the mundane right view
which is recognizing
there is good action, there is bad
action that literally means ah so
there's a difference like it by the way
action can be same externally.
Yeah. But there is a difference whether
that action is rooted in absence of
desire, absence of greed, aversion,
delusion or is it rooted in greed,
aversion, delusion. You do the same
thing externally. It's two different
actions because you stop judging action
by the content. You start seeing it by
the motivation behind which are its
necessary presently enduring roots.
That that's the thing. So I was always
struck by the fact that
the common sense tells you that you've
got an action. We say so you're talking
about like observing an action
externally. So that person is walking
over there and that person is also
walking over there. So they're doing the
same thing externally, the same action,
but they're doing it for different
reason. He's going over there to get
away from something and he's going over
there cuz he wants something whatever.
So you distinguish them between the
acts. the action, the external action
and the motivation. And what you're
saying is motivation is more important.
But actually the Buddha says the action
is the motivation.
They're not two different things. So
actually to talk about the external act
is kind of
well that's not even an action.
Yeah, that's what I mean. So that's why
he says chaitana is
well the action is
action. No, that's what I'm saying. Like it's
No, that's what I'm saying. Like it's
not
like what you described is the common
sense. Yeah. But that's not what action is.
Yeah. But that's not what action is.
Exactly. Yeah.
So, so
yeah, every action is intention.
Yeah. So, your intention is your action. Even
So, your intention is your action. Even
if you don't make a physically uh
discernable, visible by others action.
Yeah. You're already committed to that action
You're already committed to that action
through your intention.
So, everyone's measure of this external
action. Oh, this is what he does and we
can observe externally. It's not
it's measuring the results of action.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It's measuring
that which is basically rooted in that
which is which is if you think that's
what action is, you're not going to see
what action really is which is the
intention that binds it all like
throughout so to speak.
Think of the intention as the container
of all the acts by body, speech and mind
you do within that context of intended
resulting consequence.
the the example there's an example that
Venbulan came up with in his early writings was
came up with in his early writings was
you you someone you make someone's
drinking a cup of tea and they they
could put a spoonful of sugar into their
tea and you're watching this and you know
and you're watching this and you know
that that's arsenic
so you think why why is he killing
himself so you your measure for what it is this
so you your measure for what it is this
external what's going on out there
yeah It's not the act because he doesn't
know it's arson.
And if people are when people are not
aware of their own motivation, then they
start assuming motivation of others
simply based on the observing of the
external acts.
And we spoke about it in other talks
where somebody would have
unacceptable speech and people would
just assume ill will and anger and
conceit yet is another.
Yeah. And you will be much more kind of
And you will be much more kind of
prolific in the to the in the extent of
that assuming other people motivation.
Yeah. The more you become aware of your own,
The more you become aware of your own,
well, the more accurate in the reading
become without needing to assume it.
Yeah. Because now you know you're becoming
Because now you know you're becoming
familiar with how motivation works
really. So that's what I mean the action is not
So that's what I mean the action is not
what you've done. The action is the
intention within which is something
you've done.
Yeah. So again back that's why it's a mundane
So again back that's why it's a mundane
right view.
Yeah. It's because it's already aligning
It's because it's already aligning
itself with what the right view is. You
start recognizing where the work is,
where the importance is. You start
recognizing the criteria what for what
is wholesome and for what is unh
wholesome. And and that criteria for
people is external
when they start. It's all you shouldn't
do that. You must do this. Doesn't
matter why.
Yeah. You just must adhere to this form, to
You just must adhere to this form, to
this method, to this technique and then
it's right. It's not.
Yeah. You can adhere to the technique the rest
You can adhere to the technique the rest
of your life for completely wrong
reasons. And that's why you will not
even have a mundane right view.
Yeah. Let alone be free from suffering.
Let alone be free from suffering.
So yeah. And so and the important thing
is this mundane right view. It's not
it's mundane. It's like it's it's um
it's not mundane like common.
No, but it's but
it's more like it doesn't pertain to
that universal from suffering. You could
say there are even there are people who
have no interest in
and are closer to the mundane idea
because they're more straightforward in
their you know because the thinking does
not violate the basic principles of that
like universal nature of things. Yeah,
they're looking at what they're doing.
Why am I doing this? What's
the whole the whole thing the whole
thing of that description that mundane
right view like there is given there's
all these things means exactly that oh
things are rooted not in what you
observed but things are rooted in basically
but things are rooted in basically
motivation behind it. Now, as I said
many times before, certain things
externally done always have to be rooted
in certain intentions such as killing,
stealing, cheating, uh whatever sexual
intercourse from the point of view of of
of a celibate person and so on. You
abandon that. But everything else is
determined by the intention behind not
by the content of what you're doing. So
like there is mother, there is father,
yeah, there is good, there is bad, there
there is responsibility for my own
actions as in oh responsibility for me walking,
as in oh responsibility for me walking,
sitting, talking, doing this is on me,
not on the reasoning that I have towards
the world, so to speak. When people say,
"Oh, well, no, I went there because such
and such said so that I should do it."
Yeah, you might do that. You might
choose for that to be the reason for
your action, but you will not be able to
ignore that. You are responsible for
choosing that such and such person said
something and that was your reason for
going because you can always say no to
it. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah.
Yeah. Exactly. Yeah.
So yeah. So the the this the usual state
of affairs is someone places authority
over their life over what they do
or people induce that impersonal
authority because it helps them uh
alleviate that responsibility.
Tell me what to do.
Oh, I do that because that's what we do
here. That's what we do in this society.
That's what we do in this culture. No,
you choose to do what the society does
or you choose to uh not do.
I could always say no to that. I could
always say no to the group.
Exactly. So the point is not to like go
with the group or against the group or
neither should always say no to the
group. Yeah.
The point is to recognize that you're
responsible for whatever you choose to
do. Exactly. Whether I say yes or no, it's
Exactly. Whether I say yes or no, it's
my choice.
And you cannot
abstain from choosing. They will then
abstain you from responsibility for your
choice. Because saying I will not choose
is your choice. My choice is to abstain
from choice A and choice B.
Oh. So you're responsible for abstaining
Yeah. So why would why do people then
avoid responsibility for choice? It's
unpleasant. Yeah,
Yeah,
it feels a little bit
primordial perfect form of duka.
Yeah, duka literally means opposite of suka
duka literally means opposite of suka
means disease or unease. It's not you
know suffering and despair of the world.
No, it's that uneasiness in regard to
everything. Yeah. Because literally everything that
Yeah. Because literally everything that
you experience
is of that universal nature of it's not
in my control
and that's why it makes me uneasy.
So you can you have two ways of going
about it. Either pretend it's not there,
ignore it.
Mhm. Which you can only do as a starting
Which you can only do as a starting
point so to speak. We all start by
ignoring the ignoring the universal
truth of that nature
which then obviously results in
everything else the self craving desire
lust that then fuels it even more.
So can we say like so Sra would call
that bad faith.
Yeah. Yeah. It's a form of faith
like literally you have thing right in
front of your face and you pretend it's
not there.
I believe that this that this it's not
there. It's already your existence. It's
already a contradiction in terms
I believe that these things they were
given to me. My feelings have a reason
for me. Perceptions have a reason for
me. I believe I have created them by
being the master and controller.
Yet you have no say in them. But you
still while not having say in these
things you feel you still maintain the
notion that you are the owner of what
you feel.
And then you ignore everything else that
would contradict that ownership.
And that's why
dooka cannot enter you. You cannot be
liable to it, exposed to it unless you
make yourself so.
Mhm. So through ignoring what's
obviously there,
lack of control, lack of safety, lack of
easiness. That's why you become subjected to lack
That's why you become subjected to lack
of safety. That's why you become unsafe
and uneasy
and so on.
And the reason you ignore it is because
it's unpleasant.
But because of that, you experience even
more unpleasure.
Yeah. This great mass of suffering as the
This great mass of suffering as the
weather would say. So you realize, oh,
so you have no choice about this
pleasure. You have only choice about how much of
You have only choice about how much of
it. and you realize well if I actually
accept this which now seems worse the
the the displeasure of anxiety and
uneasiness and lack of control and
endure it I'm actually overcoming all
the other suffering there would be as a
result of avoiding this
hence even as a mundane right view of a
puja you would be doing already undoing
a lot of already removing a lot of dust
from your eyes a lot of wrong views and
other dependencies on greed aversion and
delusion
So suffering is right there. Liability
to suffering is right there. As I said,
would you be able to experience any form
of suffering, any form of pain, any form
of discomfort
if you don't have a desire for anything
you gained or anything you lost?
So then if the only reason you give into
desire is to be free from pain yet
desire is the reason for any form of
pain why don't you just abandon the
desire and thus you abandon the pain
and thus you abandon the pain
cuz that is your goal all along
right from the start the the worst
without any inclination to practice the
dharma and the best the purest the
greatest of the other hands same
motivation to be free from pain.
Mhm. It's just how they go about it
trying to avoid it or not not
appropriate. So the transparency we talk about then
So the transparency we talk about then
is about undoing these contradictions
that you carry already within yourself
that are making you liable to suffering.
It's not about figuring out the truth at
the end of your meditation retreat that
would then result in cancellation of all
the contradictions and the problems that
make you suffer.
There are lot I mean there are lots
there are kind of more there are grosser
types of bad faith that people will
well bad faith is as endless as a VJ is
cuz that's what a VJ is.
So for example someone might
in order to ignore something to turn a
blind eye to it you need to know that
there is at least that thing there.
Yeah. You cannot ignore that which does not
You cannot ignore that which does not
exist.
Yeah. Yeah. That's the weird thing.
You're kind of lying to yourself but how
can you lie to yourself cuz you know
Yeah. Well, yeah. That's exactly how
that's why people suffer. That's why
people would suffer on account of what
other people say or do because it would
remind them of the stuff they're trying
to cover up for themsel.
If you're free from any form of
existential cover up, there is nothing
that can provoke you or engage you or
affect you.
Nothing. If you don't crave safety, how could you
If you don't crave safety, how could you
possibly suffer on account of lack of
safety? If you don't create control, if you
If you don't create control, if you
don't imply control, if you don't assume
control, how can you suffer on account
of random things happening to you?
And by the way, when I say control, I
don't mean controlling the world or the
things. I mean, people assume control
over their own feelings while at the
same time, simultaneously, they know
they have no say in those feelings
arising. They know they're subjected to
it. But even that recognition of I'm
But even that recognition of I'm
subjected to feeling they put within
their assumption of control.
Yeah. They get the order wrong.
They get the order wrong.
Exactly.
Exactly. And that's how often the Buddha would
And that's how often the Buddha would
ask people who would have approached him
like that.
Ah, so you are in control of which
feeling is then in your control?
Is it pleasant or is it unpleasant or
the the neutral one? Because they
they're always one of them can only be
present, not all of them.
Yeah. So if if you are in the control of
So if if you are in the control of
pleasant feeling, how come then it
changes into unpleasant one?
If you're in control of unpleasant, how
come it changes into neutral?
Yeah. That's say when you sort of you
can be reminded that yeah no actually
I'm not in control of these feelings.
Yeah. And the reason why people avoid
such reminders is cuz they're
unpleasant. Yeah.
Yeah.
So you trying to outrun discomfort of
certain recognitions within yourself is
basically you trying to control your
feelings. Yeah. You think you are in a position to
Yeah. You think you are in a position to
outrun that which you're subjected to.
Yeah. You're ignoring it. You're turning
a blind eye to it. You're pretending
it's not there. You're trying to cover
up with a set of feelings you want.
So you're kind of living a
contradiction. Yeah. Well, that's what BA is. B is a
Yeah. Well, that's what BA is. B is a
contradiction.
You remove the contradiction. The
existence is ceased.
Contradiction free.
Yeah. The transparency begins by
acknowledging the contradictions and they and like you
the contradictions and they and like you
said,
Exactly. Exactly. Yeah. Yeah. But for
most people I mean it's just a
So you recognize what's what's what's
the first what would be the most common
contradiction of of say a lay person wants to start
of of say a lay person wants to start
practicing the dharma. The contradiction
they have to start saying no to
the contradiction they have to start
saying no to.
Yeah. To start rounding it up start
abstaining from precepts.
Exactly. So here you are wanting to develop
So here you are wanting to develop
freedom from suffering on a counter
practicing from the dharma.
Yeah. And um and I'm still doing this.
And um and I'm still doing this.
Yeah. So I want to develop basically the
strength of mind.
Yeah. They will be immovable.
They will be immovable.
Yeah.
In regard to anything that I might be
subjected to,
but in the meantime I will keep acting
out of my weakness.
Yeah. In order to develop strength.
In order to develop strength.
Yeah. That's a contradiction in terms.
Yeah. Like you want to heal your itchy
skin, infected whatever ulcers that are
very itchy, you have to stop start
scratching and making it worse. As
simple as that. You still don't know
necessarily what the actual cure might
be, but you would already know you
should stop making it worse.
Mhm. Cuz one thing for sure, even if you find
Cuz one thing for sure, even if you find
the cure later on, it won't work cuz you
destroyed your whole arm with your
scratching. So you already know that certain types
So you already know that certain types
of behavior are rooted in being unable
to control yourself, unable to restrain
yourself. Yet here you are practicing
for the ultimate immovability, the
ultimate kind of restraint in regard to
giving into pain, giving into pleasure,
giving into anything that move. You want
peace on account of which you keep
disturbing yourself.
Yeah. You basically want to you're
looking for freedom from ill will, from
sense desire. And yet you give in to ill
will and sense desire cuz you want to be
free from
you're acting.
That's what I mean. Like if both sensual
craving, desire, and ill will were not
originally and fundamentally unpleasant.
You wouldn't be feeling pressured to
deal with it.
Yeah. And that's what Buddha said. Those acts,
And that's what Buddha said. Those acts,
those those um those experiences
are always underlined by that craving,
by more of that craving.
And that's how you know that you are
pressured. Yeah. And and so like you might crave
Yeah. And and so like you might crave
for pleasure, but the only reason you
crave for that central pleasure is cuz
simultaneously underneath it, you crave
crave for freedom from the current in.
Yeah. Yeah. So the context of me is I
don't want this pain of not having that
thus I'll crave for that.
Yeah. So it's what you're craving towards it.
So it's what you're craving towards it.
It's underlined by even more craving.
They're both simultaneously there and
one feeds the other.
Yeah. But looking at this thing that you're
But looking at this thing that you're
heading towards allows you to ignore.
Exactly. And allows you like that hope that that
And allows you like that hope that that
will be the escape of this current pain.
Yeah. That's why the sensuality is on
the level of assumption.
That's the gratification.
That's the gratification. Not getting
it, but hoping that getting it will free
you from it.
And that's why sensuality is the
assumption. As I said,
yeah, it's not deriving pleasure from sense
it's not deriving pleasure from sense
objects is not what sensuality is.
Yeah. It's assuming that pleasure
It's assuming that pleasure
simultaneously craving for avoiding the
pain of not having it. Hence, it's on
the level of a view.
Yeah. So the first contradiction a lay
person has to undo is the contradiction
of uh lack of restraint. Contradiction
of not keeping the precepts.
That's a contradiction to your own goal
of wanting to practice the dharma.
Yeah. But ask yourself like even if you're not
But ask yourself like even if you're not
sure well first you have to be you have
to read the sutras and become familiar
with what the actual goal of dharma is.
But say even you are somewhere in
between you're unclear ask yourself what
enlightenment would what would
enlightenment entail for me? Yeah,
that's it. That's what I was thinking. I
think there's so many contradictions you
can think of that that
play for
and by ignoring
or by not making effort to develop
clarity in regard to these things, you
are automatically
maintaining contradiction. So you don't
need to make the effort to oh I I I'll
keep this contradiction. All you need to
do is ignore it and that's how you're
keeping it. So
I say it's quite common the idea of so I
want to practice for enlightenment
and yet enlightenment is this thing that
will happen to me
um
out of my control.
Out of my control if I do these things
if I do this thing here then something
I'll be lucky
other will suddenly happen to me.
Yeah. So that's already the first thing you
So that's already the first thing you
should start questioning.
Yeah. Well, you might want to believe
that that's how enlightenment works,
but then if you read the sutas, you
realize that's not what the Buddha said.
Well, then reading suit. So, most people
probably don't read the sutas. So, I
want to practice as the I want to I
think the Buddha is probably on to
something, but I won't find out.
but I won't find out.
I won't find out. That's another
contradiction. So, exactly.
I want to practice the Buddhist
teaching, but I also don't want to make
the effort to find out what the teaching
clearly is. Yeah, I'll just hope that
these other people that talk about
So that's another lack of transparency.
Yeah. And that will also prevent you from
And that will also prevent you from
being clear about your own motives.
But if you start investigating your
motives, as I said, your goal will
become clearer. If your goal of
practicing dam is clear, then it will
make obvious sense to invest effort in
finding out what that dharma is.
But even if you're not there,
even though it's even though it's quite
a difficult thing to do, there's so many
books there, so many things to read. But
start to start.
It shouldn't stop me.
Exactly. Means like oh yeah okay so
that's the extent of the work that needs
to be done not like oh it's too much of
it thus I won't do any of it.
Yeah. Yeah. It's not that's just what's
and that's what I said many times like a
person who recognize what for his own
welfare as in whether I engage with
sensuality whether I don't engage with
sensuality either way I suffer
which suffering can has greater prospect
of resulting in sessation of suffering
engaging with centrality and prolonging
desire or abstaining from it. So he
already didn't have the direction. Then
that person would go and find those who
teach abstaining from sensuality
to learn more about it.
Then he would ponder on what they said.
Then he would get a sense of it. Having
a sense of it, then he says he measures
the task.
Oh, it becomes clearer to him what needs
to be done.
When you know what needs to be done, he
sets to do it.
And the reason why people don't know
what dama practice is because they never
made the effort to really find out what
that task is.
Yeah. Well, unfortunately
Well, unfortunately
all the effort they made was invested in
the wrong direction.
So that's the thing. So people hope
Yeah. that just by listening to this talk on
that just by listening to this talk on
YouTube or that will just spark
that'll give me all the knowledge I
need. Yeah.
Yeah. So you ask yourself what is what is
So you ask yourself what is what is
enlightenment for me?
What do I think it is? Or I want
enlightenment. What do I want through
that enlightenment? What is the what is
the sort of what is the goal of going
towards? What is the result of it?
What is the result of it?
Is it permanent pleasure?
Okay. Permanent pleasure in what form?
Like permanent central pleasure or
permanent peaceful pleasure?
I guess it's permanent peaceful
pleasure. So what is the main
characteristic of the like permanent
peace? Oh, it's absence of disturbances.
Absence of what disturbances? while
absence of disturbance is that I know
and see and hear and smell and taste and
touch and are unable to be indifferent
to words.
So which is more likely then? Would the
perfect peace come as a result of you
preventing smell, smell, taste, touch
and all the other senses? Or would
perfect peace come as a result of you
learning how to be unmoved in regard to
smell, sense, and everything else?
Which one makes more sense?
Well, being unmoved makes more sense.
So, why don't I start practicing lack of
moving in regard to things right here, right
in regard to things right here, right
now that move me?
Mhm. Has would that have a greater prospect
Has would that have a greater prospect
of pertaining to sensuality that you
already value
through your own random efforts?
Yeah. But now it's not some random anymore.
But now it's not some random anymore.
Yeah.
You actually well reasoned, well
contemplated, and you're already getting
a sense of direction, which means you're
already getting a sense of what needs to
be done. Yeah. And what you're doing
there is clearer, more transparent.
Exactly. And doesn't depend on on other people
And doesn't depend on on other people
and doesn't depend on the circumstances.
It's in regard to the circumstances.
That's and that's the whole point.
That's what Buddha said. Whatever is to
be obtained by oneself, by one's manly
effort, manly strength, manly endurance,
I obtained I'm an arant. I'm full
enlightenment. Around is something you developed, not
Around is something you developed, not
something that happens to you. And
that's why it cannot be taken away from
you. In the same sense, pleasant feeling
has arisen. You're subjected to it and
then it disappeared. It's taken away
from you.
But if you developed your mind in regard
to manifestation, in regard to arising
of anything, feeling, perception,
intention, sight, sound, smell, taste,
touch, thought, whatever.
It's not dependent on the content of it,
but it's dependent on your attitude
towards it. You realize you will be
immovable in regard to anything and
everything. Even the most extreme
examples that are listed in the sutas or
being killed and butchered and your mind
composure will not change.
And that's possible because your
practice has ceased to pertain to the
circumstances to the senses but it
started looking at the nature of it in
regard to which you train your
immovability impetability.
And that training starts when you're
completely unenlightened.
You don't you don't magically slot into
it when you develop the right view. You
develop the right view because you've
been training rightly.
So can you say
so it's it's quite common
to I think for people to think that
practicing the dharma is involves not
thinking involves kind of
thinking thinking thinking is the
problem yeah you're overthinking these
things just
yeah well the question you should
immediately ask yourself there is
so if it's just about doing it where is
the motivation for doing rooted
is it rooted in doing or is it rooted in
thought behind your doing.
Yeah. So that's
yet here you are ignoring thought on
account of your doing means you ignore
the reason for motivation which means
you ignore what action is
and somehow you're hoping to free
yourself from action. So basically,
if someone wants to really start
practicing in line with the dharma,
if they're not already, which you
probably are if you're listening to
these videos, but
it's about kind of No, I do need to
start thinking about my motivation cuz
that's that where DA is.
Yeah. My motivation for there is I'm not
My motivation for there is I'm not
justified in doing anything or not doing
anything. I have no justification for
anything. Whatever I do or whatever I choose not
Whatever I do or whatever I choose not
to do, it's because I made a choice for
which I'm responsible.
Thus, I'm not justified or absolved from
that responsibility.
So, I want to practice dharma. Okay.
Why? Oh, because I want to be from
suffering. Okay. So, what's important is
my responsibility. I'm responsible for
what's important.
Basically recognizing that
responsibility, not running away from
it, not covering it up because it's
unpleasant. Accepting that uneasiness
like you're responsible yet you're not
in control. It's a very uneasy
situation. Yeah. Literally, if I tell you, oh, if
Yeah. Literally, if I tell you, oh, if
something happens to such and such
person, if they do something stupid,
you'll pay the price.
Yeah. Yeah.
That's basically what is responsible.
That's what samsara is. That's what
existence is. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's a good way of
putting it.
You have to recognizing that existential
responsibility is the gateway for the
direction of the dharma.
You can spend 50 years practicing the
dharma. If you haven't started that
practice through that gateway, there is
no dharma in your practice.
And if that upsets you hearing that,
well, it just confirms
that you haven't developed freedom from
suffering. You haven't developed
imperturbability in regard to
circumstances, which is words of others.
Mhm. Like is my practice freeing me from
Like is my practice freeing me from
suffering? Not by controlling the
circumstances, preventing the exposure
to things they might have said to me,
but through me being unable to move,
unable to suffer, unable to despair on
account of things I cannot escape.
Thus, you will not need an escape
anymore as in in trying to outrun sight sounds,
as in in trying to outrun sight sounds,
smell, deny them through refusing to
think about them and so on. You cannot
suffer either way. That's truly the
burdenless. Oh, I don't need to do
anything. There's no burden for me. when
I see this, I must do this. When I think
that, I must run this way.
Could you Could you say that's the kind
of that sense of self is almost that's
what it is? It's that escape. It's that
kind of safety.
safety.
It's a product.
Yeah. Of your dependence on looking for
Of your dependence on looking for
of the assumption that there is some y
that's the direct product. That's what I
mean. Sense of self is not a problem.
It's a symptom.
Yeah. And you want to approve that symptom.
And you want to approve that symptom.
Well, you stop maintaining it. to stop
ignoring sankara
uh being uh the duka and being a niche
and being duka as in being not in my
control and being uneasy you stop
ignoring non-control and uneasiness you
will stop maintaining this is mine this
is myself
even if you don't necessarily think
about oh now I must practice anata anata
will be the result of you not supporting
ata through your own actions and
thinking and so
So start undoing contradictions.
Yeah, that's
and that will result in the right view
and then that will result in our own.
So
the fundamental fundamental
contradictions sorry is what we said
like you don't need to chase down all
the contradictions in the world. No,
start with the ones that are like more
obvious to you based on whatever
faculties you have but fundamentally
bring them all home so to speak. What is
the fundamental contradiction
of this body?
Well, that I assume control over it and
yet I'm not in control of it.
That you assume and like the the life
that depends upon the operating body.
Yeah. Can that be in your control?
Can that be in your control?
Yeah. So,
yeah. Is that is that a context that you
have at the back of your mind throughout
your day
that you're not in control on your own
body, let alone of your own life? Or is
that a context that you kind of drift
away from and forget about and ignore?
That's all it takes. You don't need to
make extra effort towards ignorance. All
you need to do is ignore the right
thing. That's how you're investing in
ignorance already.
All you need to do is lose the sight of
the context that you're not in control
of this body.
If you lose that sight, automatically
you're assuming control.
Automatically you're acting out of greed
delusion. So, so it's not just so learning not to
So, so it's not just so learning not to
tolerate contradictions, but also
learning to recognize them because you
for for so long you've
allowed them to be there without
actually and you will recognize them when you
and you will recognize them when you
learn how to endure them and not give
into them.
Yeah. So, when you learn to endure the
uneasiness Yeah.
Yeah.
And again, the first uneasiness you're
going to get is the uneasiness of
starting to keep the precepts.
And you might you might first of all
that those contradictions might be
gross, might be quite obvious,
but maybe that's where you need to
start. But what you're saying is like,
well, there will be more deep rooted
and if you wonder where the
contradictions are, well, just ask
yourself, have you been acting out of
desire recently? Have you committed any
act by body, speech, or mind out of
desire? That's your contradiction
already. Yeah.
Desire implies ownership implies that
result. Do you feel any shame?
Do you feel any shame?
Yeah.
Do you see the danger that desire? No.
That's another contradiction cuz it's
dangerous. Yeah.
Yeah.
Here you are riding on this body as if
you created it. You're in control. Yet
you have no idea even how components
operate. And if something interferes with it,
And if something interferes with it,
that's it. Your ride is gone.
Yeah. It's finished. And you know that. That's
It's finished. And you know that. That's
why death is so terrifying for people.
Not because death is terrifying itself,
but because literally your entire
existence ignores it.
The more you ignore it, the more power
it has.
So when that transparency is developed
sufficiently enough then literally
becomes obvious
is obvious. That's why the declaration
of course whatever has the nature to
manifest for that very reason it's not
in my control. because it's manifested.
That's why it will cease. Nothing else.
Then you just cultivate that same thing
and any traces of any desire, any little
contradictions or discrepancies gone.